ELNUR GASANOV

Thuwal, Saudi Arabia \diamond elnur.gasanov@kaust.edu.sa \diamond https://elnurgasanov.com

PUBLICATIONS

Error Feedback Shines when Features are Rare

Peter Richtárik, <u>Elnur Gasanov</u>, Konstantin Burlachenko https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.15264

Understanding Progressive Training Through the Framework of Randomized Coordinate Descent

Rafał Szlendak, Elnur Gasanov, Peter Richtárik

https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.03626

Adaptive Compression for Communication-Efficient Distributed Training

Maksim Makarenko, Elnur Gasanov, Abdurakhmon Sadiev, Rustem Islamov, Peter Richtárik

- Transactions on Machine Learning Research (accepted)
- https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.00188

3PC: Three Point Compressors for Communication-Efficient Distributed Training and a Better Theory for Lazy Aggregation

Peter Richtárik, Igor Sokolov, Ilyas Fatkhullin, Elnur Gasanov, Zhize Li, Eduard Gorbunov

- Proceedings of the 39th International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML 2022)
- https://arxiv.org/abs/2202.00998

FLIX: A Simple and Communication-Efficient Alternative to Local Methods in Federated Learning Elnur Gasanov, Ahmed Khaled, Samuel Horvath, Peter Richtárik

- Proceedings of the 25th International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics (AISTATS 2022)
- https://arxiv.org/abs/2111.11556

Lower Bounds and Optimal Algorithms for Smooth and Strongly Convex Decentralized Optimization Over Time-Varying Networks

Dmitry Kovalev, Elnur Gasanov, Alexander Gasnikov, Peter Richtárik

- Proceedings of the 35th Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS 2021)
- https://arxiv.org/abs/2106.04469

From Local SGD to Local Fixed-Point Methods for Federated Learning

Grigory Malinovsky, Dmitry Kovalev, Elnur Gasanov, Laurent Condat, Peter Richtárik

- Proceedings of the 37th International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML 2020)
- https://arxiv.org/abs/2004.01442

Stochastic Spectral and Conjugate Descent Methods

Dmitry Kovalev, Eduard Gorbunov, Elnur Gasanov, Peter Richtárik

- Proceedings of the 32th Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS 2018)
- https://arxiv.org/abs/1802.03703

Creation of approximating scalogram description in a problem of movement prediction Elnur Gasanov, Anastasia Motrenko

- "Machine Learning and Data Analysis", Vol. 3, #2, 2017
- http://jmlda.org/papers/doc/2017/no2/Gasanov2017ECoGAnalysis.pdf (in russian)

CAREER SYNOPSIS

Ph.D. researcher at the Artificial Intelligence Initiative, KAUST, specializing in Distributed Learning. Authored numerous peer-reviewed papers, especially featured in top conferences such as ICML and NeurIPS. Honored with the Dean's List Award for academic distinction at KAUST.

Teaching Assistant at the Federated Learning course.

EDUCATION

Ph.D. in Computer Science

Jan. 2020 - Present

King Abdullah University of Science and Technology, Thuwal, Saudi Arabia Research Focus: Compression and Personalization for Federated Learning Academic PI: Peter Richtárik

Master of Science in Computer Science

Sep. 2018 - Dec. 2019

 $King\ Abdullah\ University\ of\ Science\ and\ Technology,\ Thuwal,\ Saudi\ Arabia$

GPA: 3.67/4.00

Bachelor of Science in Applied Mathematics and Physics

Sep. 2014 - Jun. 2018

Moscow Institute of Physics and Technology, Moscow, Russia

Average Grade: 8.66/10.00

AWARDS AND RECOGNITIONS

| Invited to give a talk at a Federated Learning course | University of Tartu, Estonia | 2023 |
|--|---------------------------------|------------|
| CEMSE Dean's List Award (Top 20%) | KAUST, Saudi Arabia | 2022 |
| Best Reviewer Award (Top 10%) at ICML 2022 | ICML Program Chairs, USA | 2022 |
| KAUST Fellowship for MS/PhD students | KAUST, Saudi Arabia | 2018 |
| Increased State Academic Scholarship | Ministry of Education, Russia | 2017 |
| Academic Excellence Scholarship | Non-profit Fund, Russia | 2014-2017 |
| Prize-Winner of "Future Scientists" | Moscow State University, Russia | 2014 |
| Prize-Winner of Economics Olympiad at the Regional Level | Ministry of Education, Russia | 2013 |
| Prize-Winner of Physics Olympiad at the Regional Level | Ministry of Education, Russia | 2012-2014 |
| Prize-Winner of Math Olympiad at the Regional Level | Ministry of Education, Russia | 2012, 2014 |

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Ph.D. Researcher 01/2020 - Present

King Abdullah University of Science and Technology, Artificial Intelligence Initiative

Conducted research in Distributed Learning, collaborating with a team of 15+ researchers. Published 5 papers in peer-reviewed conferences and journals. Utilized various Python packages (JAX, FedJAX, Optax) in computational experiments. Recognized with the Dean's List Award (Top 20%) for outstanding academic performance.

Teaching Assistant 09/2023 - 09/2023

King Abdullah University of Science and Technology, KAUST Academy

Course: Federated Learning, Professor Peter Richtárik

Facilitated hands-on lab exercises, enhancing student understanding and practical skills. Designed and prepared two comprehensive lab exercises to supplement course material.

Research Scientist Intern

06/2019 - 07/2019

University of Grenoble-Alpes, Laboratory Jean Kuntzmann

Developed asynchronous lock-free algorithms for gradient descent, deriving convergence rates for both full and stochastic gradient cases. Analyzed the algorithm with constant and diminishing stepsizes.

SKILLS

Mathematical Calculus, Linear Algebra, Algorithm Theory, Deep Learning

Computational Python, JAX, FedJAX, PyTorch

Tools LaTeX, Git

Languages English (Advanced), Russian (Native)

EXTRA CURRICULARS AND HOBBIES

Hobbies: Fitness, Volleyball

Volunteer: National Park Hunsrueck II, Deuselbach, Germany, 2017

Volunteer: Environment and Legality at Vesuvio National Park, Ottaviano, Italy, 2016

Volunteer: University "5top100" conference, 2016

Volunteer: Promoting Biodiversity in Neckertal, Brunnadern SG, Switzerland, 2015